Guide to the Centennial Oral History Project Oral Histories 1982-1988
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 1: One-on-one Interviews
  - Landis, Paul Sociology, Rural Sociology, Dean of Graduate School, March 1, 1984; Miller, Isabel; 15 tapes (Box 11)
    #1) Family background. Sociology Department. Published works. WSU career, 1935-. Previous teaching and job experiences. #2) Soc. Dep't. - colleagues, students, social work program, development of the Rural Soc. Dep't. Government project works. Public attitudes toward soc. Family life in Pullman. Great Depression and westward migration to Washington. Research. #3) Soc. Dep't. - colleagues, course load. Holland administration. Landis' deanship - Graduate School. Compton admn. Resignation from deanship. Compton's real estate developments. #4) Real estate, cont'd. Colleagues. Changed atmosphere on campus during & after WWII. Student Strike, 1936. Veterans as students. Gov't programs during Depression. Compton's demise. Pullman community. Landis' real estate development. #5) Landis' real estate, cont'd. Graduate exams. Graduate faculty. His deanship. Graduate language requirement. Committee system within departments. Work with Farm Home Administration (FHA) during WWII. #6) FHA, cont'd. Effects of WWII on campus. Landis' real estate development. Landis' college employment. WSU career. #7 & #8) Landis' sabbaticals around the world, esp. Africa. #9) Sabbaticals. His achievement drive. Much on family and background. #10) Family & background. #11) Family & background. Hunting trips. His diet. Landis' children. #12) His children and grandchildren. #13) Children, grandchildren. Relationship between Pullman and WSU. Much on his real estate developments & role in building Pullman. Corrections & insertions by Landis. His declining health. #14) Landis' declining health and attitude toward it. Reflects on life's rewards and his failures. Reflects on his wife, Bess. Family members and their health. Graduate School. Sociology Department - facilities. Retirement. #15) Landis' teaching career. Reflects on Bess, his marriage, and fatherhood.
  - Law, Alvin G. Agronomy and Soils, August 14, 19857; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 3 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal background. Impressions of WSU, 1941-79. Courses Law taught. Origins and work of Washington State Crop Improvement Association. Facilities. Observations of Law on bridging gap between academics and agricultural industries. Various faculty and ag. extension staff. Role of a land-grant university. Seed and turf research at WSU. Work as Vice Chairman of Agronomy and Soils. Collegiate Crops Judging, participants and coaches. Law's outlook on foreign service. Law's views on consulting as a professional agronomist. Law's reflections on his experiences.
    Journal article about Law. Photo of Law teaching, 1960. Photo of Alvin and Roberta Law, 1985. Photo of Law and Bertramson, 1985.
  - Lawrence, John M. Institute of Biological Chemistry, November 20, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1948-81. Ag. Chemistry department (later named Institute of Biological Chemistry) - faculty, chairmen, and facilities. Shift in departmental research emphasis from nutrition and foods to plant biochemistry. Formation of Biological chemistry. Members at outlying stations. Retirement work with Department of Agronomy and Soils. Hobbies and recreation. Retrospection of life at WSU and Pullman.
  - Lincoln, Keith Alumni - Physical Education, 1961. Assistant Football Coach, January 30, 1986; Fry, Dick; 2 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal background. Football at WSU. Professional football with the San Diego Chargers. Coaching at different levels-high school, college, professional. Teammates and outstanding players at WSU and San Diego. Sid Gillman, Charger coach. [Lincoln was a WSU student from 1957 to 1961. He returned to WSU as an assistant football coach, 1971 to 1973. Lincoln then transfered to the Alumni Center in 1973, and currently is the Director - though not discussed in the interview].
  - Littlewood, Robert A. Anthropology, February 6, 1986; Dahl, Kathleen; 1 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal background. Sociology%Anthropology Department - faculty, locations, tensions, and unity. Anthropology boom of the 1960s. Faculty government and problems with French and Terrell administrations. Salaries and economics of WSU. Future needs of the program and the university.
  - Liu Maoling Electrical Engineering, November 19, 1984; Knox, R. Frank; 1 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal background - born and raised in China, and experiences in a tuberculosis sanitarium. Immigration problems. WSU career, 1958-1969. Electrical Engineering department and faculty. Locations of EE, math, and architecture departments, and the development of laboratories. Administrative personnel. Graduate students and secretaries. Retirement.
  - Loreen, C. Oscar Vocational Agriculture, January 15, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 12)
    Recollections of Vocational Agriculture, 1920-80. Loreen's biography. Development of young farmer education. Origins and development of FFA. Dedicated Washington Vo-Ag teachers. Locations of the Vocational Agriculture department on the WSU campus. FFA annual convention. Loreen's philosophy of Vocational Agriculture extention training.
    Loreen's 1980 paper for a Future Farmers of America convention on agricultural education entitled "An Association of Long Standing: Washington State University and the FFA."
  - Manring, Betty H. Alumni - Liberal Arts, 1932, July 31, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 2 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal and family background. 1932 Los Angeles Olympics and Hollywood. The Depression. Social life on campus. Campus housing. Courses and faculty. Emphasis on proper etiquette. WSU YWCA. Extension Service and 4-H. Manring's children's education and careers.
    Family tree of WSU graduates.
  - Matsen, Joseph Alumni - Business Administration, 1949, December 12, 1986; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 12)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC - changed atmosphere on campus following WWII, dormitory living, and student politics. Development of Wilson Compton Union Building.
  - Mauss, Armand Sociology, May 28, 1987; Backus, Janice; 5 tapes (Box 13)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1969-present. Sociology department - students, graduate courses, grants, facilities, research, department of Rural Sociology, and faculty. Attitude toward administration and campus service. Professional activities. Teaching versus research. Theory of teaching. Personal research. Student unrest of the 1960s. Programs - Urban Research Center, Alcohol Studies, and Religious Studies.
  - McCloskey, Gordon Education, March 16, 1982; Grunewald, Marjorie; 1 tapes (Box 13)
    Biography of McCloskey. Professional career at WSU, 1947-74. Philosophy of land-grant colleges. Student strike, circa 1970. Development of the Department of Education since 1947. WSU's role in state education. Friendship with Carl Sandburg and McCloskey's poetry. Issues facing educators today.
  - McDonough, Ellen WSU Food Services, November 27, 1984; Grunewald, Marjorie; 2 tapes (Box 13)
    McDonough's early life with sister Caroline Cooper, head of Duplicating and Mailing. Student career at WSC and WSU, 1935-82. Professional associations. Advantages and disadvantages of being a registered dietician. Changes on campus over the years. Retirement activities. Recollections of life as a child in eastern Oregon mining communities.
  - McNeil, Charles Zoology, September 16, 1985; Jonas, Robert J.; 1 tapes (Box 13)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1946-76. Courses taught by McNeil. Zoology department - research, faculty, chairs, facilities, G.I. students. WSU administration - quarter system, tenure, curriculum committee. Entomology's separation from Zoology.
  - Migaki, James Education, February 9, 1984; Grunewald, Marjorie; 2 tapes (Box 13)
    Personal background. Undergraduate years, 1949-1951. Professional career at WSU, 1967-present. Stimson Hall and YMCA. Experiences in ROTC. Experiences as a Japanese-American during WWII. Development of Asian-American program at WSU and Affirmative Action. Graduate years at WSU. Physical changes on campus over the years. Student life. Influential professors. Teaching in Spokane - first Asian-American to teach there.
  - Moree, Ray Zoology - Alumni, 1937. Professor, February 11, 1986; Jonas, R. J.; 1 tapes (Box 13)
    Personal background. Student experiences and memorable faculty at WSU, 1934-1937. WSU professional career, 1942-1977. Zoology department - courses, facilities, and research. Formation of the Entomology department. General reminiscences.
  - Morrison, Dennis Administration - Executive Assistant to President, May 19, 1986; Fry, Richard; 2 tapes (Box 13)
    Personal background. Journalism career. Professional career at WSU, 1947-85. Initial impressions of Pullman. Experience as Editor, Office of Publications. Experience as member of Agriculture Advisory Board. Working under C. Clement French. Importance of intercollegiate athletics to WSU's image. Change from college to university. Washington governors. President Compton's attitude toward salary increases. Experiences as presidential assistant to Glenn Terrell. Student unrest of the late 1960s and early 1970s. Change in student attitudes. Media reporting of student unrest.
  - Muse, Raymond (#1) History - Chair, July 7, 1986; Hall, David; 2 tapes (Box 13)
    Professional career at WSU, 1948-1979. Relationship between Political Science and History departments. The History department from 1955 to the '60s. Balance between teaching and research. Impressions of WSU students. Reminiscences of colleagues. Opinions of WSU presidents Muse worked under.
  - Muse, Raymond (#2) History - Chair, July 14, 1986; Grunewald, Marjorie; 1 tapes (Box 13)
    Personal biography. Served as first chairman of the History department, 1956-79. Service on various university committees. Muse's opinions of presidents he worked under. Muse's colleagues.
    Vita
  - Neill, Marion Alumni - Home Economics, 1936, January 21, 1987; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 14)
    Student days at WSC - Student Strike of 1936, social rules, classmates, teachers, housemothers, dress codes, job, and sororities. Home Economics department.
  - Neill, Thomas C. Alumni - Mechanical Engineering, 1938, November 7,1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 14)
    Personal background. Neill Hall. Neill family in Pullman. Entrance requirements at WSC in 1934. College living expenses. Sigma Alpha Epsilon fraternity. Memorable classes and professors. Student strike, 1936. Business in Pullman.
  - Nelson, C. Emil Agronomy and Soils, April 25, 1984; Rasmussen, Lowell W.; 3 tapes (Box 14)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU's Irrigated Agricultural Research and Extension Center (IAREC) in Prosser, WA, 1937-71. Agronomist for USDA Bureau of Plant Industry, Prosser, 1942-57. Extensive account of research activities, equipment, and facilities at IAREC. Relationship between Prosser station and the Agronomy department and faculty. Description of research farms. Nelson's feelings about his experiences and his views on research and farming.
    Biographical sketch by Nelson.
  - Nelson, Helen S. Faculty Wife - James C. Nelson, Economics, February 13, 1986; Schnaitter, Allene; 1 tapes (Box 14)
    Wife of WSU Economics Professor Emeritus, James C. Nelson. Impressions of WSC. Bob Jeffrey's school bus route. Family recreation on campus. Clubs. Education classes. Experiences teaching Social Studies and Language Arts, 1962-64, at Lincoln Middle School, and History, 1966-74, at Pullman High School. Model United Nations Assembly program and High School Bowl. Experiences as a faculty wife. Faculty Wives Association. Campus issues. Travels.
  - Nelson, James C. Economics, November 15, 1985; Schnaitter, Allene; 6 tapes (Box 14)
    Extensive personal background. Professional WSU career, 1947-1974. Reasons for coming to WSU. Development of Transportation Economics courses. Establishment of PhD program in Economics, 1959-1960. Obtaining library resources. Development of Public Utility Economics courses. Economics department - students, faculty, graduate students, and courses. Personal research, deregulation, and publications. Federal government's role in transportation.
    Nelson's entry in Who's Who in America. Letter from Vice Provost to Nelsons, commending his service to WSU; and from Brookings Institution lauding the Nelsons. Two reviews of Nelson's book, "Regulation and Competition in Transportation. Curriculum vita.
  - Northrup, Catherine Dean of Women. Associate Dean of Students, September 8, 1983; Washburn, Joanne; 3 tapes (Box 14)
    Personal background. Government Nursery School Project. Montevista schools until 1937. World War II. WSU career, 1956-1972. WSU and women students. Associated Women Students. Residence Halls. Rules and Regulations. Duties and involvements of the Dean of Women. Sexual Information Resource Center (SIRC). Student unrest of the late 1960s, early 1970s.Changes over the years regarding women's opportunities. Professional organizations.
    Personnel sheet. Five articles from local papers on her retirement - originals and copies. Dean of Women and Associate Dean of Students Annual Report, July l, 1971-June 30, 1972.
  - Oden, DuAnn Alumni - Physical Education, 1971, March 10, 1985; Jones, Barbara; 1 tapes (Box 14)
    Personal background. Physical Education curriculum. Student Health. Intercollegiate volleyball (1968-71) and basketball (1968-70). Streit-Perham residence hall. Influence of WSU on Oden's life.
  - Osburn, Orren E. Electrical Engineering, May 2, 1984; Seamans, David A.; 4 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Professional WSU career, 1922-1961. Electrical Engineering department - faculty, facilities, courses, equipment, and students. Depression years at WSC. Professional and community service - Academic Standards Committee, Boy Scouts, etc. WWII years at WSC. Retirement.
    Photograph of a DC motor tested by Osburn at General Electric. Citation of service and recognition to Osburn from the American Institute of Electrical Engineers, Spokane Section. May 18, 1956.
  - Ostrom, T.G. Mathematics - Chair, June 3, 1986; DeTemple, Duane; 1 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1960-1981. Mathematics department - teaching loads, hiring faculty, students, graduate students, class size, facilities, classes, departmental library, and grants. Perceptions of WSU and its administrations. Shift to a research-oriented university. Professional travelling experiences. Chairmanship.
  - Pence, William B. WSU Fire Department - Chief, September 12, 1985; Bennett, S. Randal; 1 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1947-75. Changes at WSU Fire Department during Pence's career. Recounts student unrest in late 1960s, early 1970s. Social activities at the Fire Department. Fire alarm systems on campus. Retirement activities.
  - Perry, Mignon Home Economics - Clothing, Interior Design, and Textiles - Chair, August 15, 1985; Klopfer, Jean M.; 1 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1958-1985. Chair, 1959-80. Changes within Clothing and Textiles department - students, emphasis on retailing, field trips, faculty, curriculum. Museum work. Off-campus graduate programs. Committee involvement. Changes within departmental structure and those involved. Home Economic's relationship with administration. Professional organizations. Perry's research and travel.
    Mignon Perry's vita.
  - Petragallo, Roy Alumni - 1930s, January 18, 1987; Stimson, William; 1 tapes (Box 15)
    Boxing at WSC in the 1930s - training, coach (Ike Deeter), teammates, and memorable fights and meets.
  - Poe, Albert Donald Architecture, February 5, 1986; Graham, Channell; 2 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Architecture employment prior to WSU. Professional WSU career, 1958-1983. Architecture department - faculty, research, and degree program. Sabbaticals. Chairmanship. Development of Construction Management Program. Professional organizations. Retirement.
  - Pratt, George W. Student, 1930s. WSU Custodian, April 26, 19871; Backus, Janice; 2 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC during the 1930s - dormitories, tuition, teachers, buildings, enrollment, classes and class size, social activities, distinguished visitors, and traditions. Work with the Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) during the Depression. Work as custodian at Wilson Compton Union Building. Organizations. Retirement.
    Photograph of George Pratt
  - Pratt, Marjorie WSU Food Services, May 19, 1987; Backus, Janice; 2 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Growing up in Pullman. Campus and summer school at WSC in 1933. Career at WSC as cook and supervisor, 1955-1980.
    Marjorie's Recipe Magic cookbook, 1974.
  - Rademacher, Peter Alumni - Animal Husbandry, 1953, April 13, 1987; Schnaitter, Allene; 2 tapes (Box 15)
    Personal background. Student days at WSU - professors, work with grounds keeper, boxing, academic work, roommates, athletics, and coaches. Marriage. Experience attending Castle Heights Military Academy. Volunteer work. Employment with Kiefer-McNeill Company. Recounts his participation in 1956 Olympics. Amateur boxing career. Return to WSU for Hall of Fame presentation and celebrations. Wife, Margaret, and their marriage. Extensive discussion of professional boxing career. Philosophy on work.
    Article, "Pete Rademacher." Chapter from uncited book, "Pete Rademacher: The Impossible Fight." Nominee information for WSU Athletic Hall of Fame. P.R. packet made by Rademacher about himself - articles, photos, and brochure on life & career.
  - Rasmussen, Lowell W. Agronomy and Soils, November 9, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 3 tapes (Box 16)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1948-75. Research and colleagues at WSU. Development of Experimental Design course. Weed and herbicides program. Organized communication with farmers. Regional weed researchers. Career as Assistant Director of Agriculture Experiment Station, 1956-75. Creation of commodity commissions and their benefits. The role & requirements of an Ag. Research Director. Regional research programs and the USDA. Relationship with State Dept. of Ag. and other agencies. Foreign service and WSU international development programs. Tribute to extension services. Outlook from 38 years at WSU. Family and social recollections.
    Vita and two photographs.
  - Sandberg, Robert Administration - Executive Assistant to President. Alumni, May 22, 1987; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 16)
    Student days at WSC during the 1930s - housing and teachers. WSU career years, 1947-1952. Story about WSU presidency being offered to Edward R. Murrow. Wilson Compton administration - moving WSU to Spokane, Compton's demise. Development of Wilson Compton Union Building.
  - Schnaitter, Allene WSU Libraries - Director, November 14, 1985; Vyhnanek, Lou; 2 tapes (Box 16)
    Personal background. Director of WSU Libraries, 1976-1984. Condition of WSU Libraries in 1976. Her administration and management style. Physical changes of the libraries. Budget crisis and WSU administration. Automation of the libraries. Role of departmental libraries. Schnaitter's reasons for stepping down because of University pressure. Current position as Coordinator of Library Development. Accomplishments and disappointments as Director.
  - Schwartze, Chester D. Horticulture - Alumni, PhD 1935. WWAREC-Puyallup, April 30, 1984; Rasmussen, Lowell W.; 2 tapes (Box 16)
    Personal background. Student at WSU, 1920-1924 (BA Agriculture), 1932-1935 (PhD Horticulture). Professional career at WSU, retired 1969. Western Washington Agricultural Research and Extension Center, Puyallup. Research - berry breeding, preservation of fruits and vegetables by freezing, and berry harvesting. Future of berry production in Washington. Cooperation with Washington Horticultural Association.
    Biographical sketch
  - Scott, David M. Architecture - Alumni, 1953. Professor and Chair, February 4, 198; Graham, Channell; 1 tapes (Box 16)
    Personal background. First impressions of WSC. Student days at WSC - professors and classmates. Professional career as an architect. Graduate school at M.I.T. Professional career at WSU, 1960-. Chair, 1966-1976. Teaching methods. Definition of architecture. Purpose of the university.
    Vita. Video tape of interview.
  - Shaw, C. Gardner Plant Pathology - Chair, November 23, 1987; Grunewald, Marjorie; 5 tapes (Box 17)
    Personal background. World War II experiences. WSU career, 1947-1983. Beaver Creek Camp development. Sabbaticals and research. Publications. Plant Pathology Department - colleagues. Experiences becoming chair and running the department. College of Agriculture administration. Grants and working with undergraduate and graduate students. Financial aid and teaching assistantships. Shaw's family. Department locations. WSU overseas projects. Recounts heart attack. Experiences as advisor of Delta Tau Delta fraternity. Shaw's contributions to his field and to WSU. Travels. Work in New Zealand and India. Professional conferences. Much on his participation in WSU's Pakistan and Jordan projects. Retirement.
  - Smith, Elizabeth (Liz) Alumni - Physical Education and Health, 1937, September 10, 1983; Washburn, Joanne; 1 tapes (Box 17)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC - impressions, work with Dr. Helen G. Smith, fees, classes, social activities, intramurals, campus grounds, and buildings. Student Strike, 1936. Professional training and career in physical therapy.
  - Smith, Floyd Alumni - Agriculture, 1913, April 10, 1987; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 17)
    Student days at WSC - boxing coach (Fred "Doc" Bohler), ROTC, Lake DePuddle, fraternities (ATO), professors, classmates, buildings, traditions, campus grounds, organizations, and clothing fashions.Personal background.
    List of Alpha Tau Omega members and their pictures, including F.R. Smith.
  - Smith, G. Donald WSU Libraries - Director, June 21, 1985; Vyhnanek, Louis; 1 tapes (Box 17)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1946-1976. Library situation upon arrival. Holland Library. Efforts and opposition to centralization of departmental libraries. Smith's directorship of the libraries. Library training. Collection development and computerization of library.
  - Smith, Helen G. Physical Education - Chair, September 8, 1983; Washburn, Joanne; 2 tapes (Box 17)
    Biography of Smith. Professional career at WSU, 1925-61. Chair, Department of Physical Education for Women. Smith Gym dedication and evolution of building plans. Department courses, activities, and faculty. Professional associations.
    Retirement article.
  - Snow, Marian Neill Alumni - Foreign Languages, 1934, August 15, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 17)
    Personal background. Family members who are WSU graduates. Student days at WSC - fees and finances, jobs, sororities, courses, student attitudes, social activities, traditions, and graduation. Snow's husband, a 1933 WSC graduate. Health care facilities. Effect of the Depression on students. Relationship between WSU and Pullman.
  - Stone, Linda S. Anthropology - Alumni. Professor, February 7, 1986; Dahl, Kathleen A.; 1 tapes (Box 17)